Register of the Aleksandr V. Samoilovich Papers, 1940-1968
Hoover Institution Archives
Aleksandr V. Samoilovich Papers,
1940-1968
2000C18
Samoilovich, Aleksandr V., 1894-
4 microfilm reels (0.6 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence and printed matter, relating to activities of the Russian Orthodox Church abroad.
Administrative Information
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2000.
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2000.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Russkaia pravoslavnaia tserkov'; Russians in foreign countries.; Russia.; Poland.; Germany.; Brazil.; United States.
Biography
Russian Orthodox priest; subsequently émigré in Poland, Germany, Brazil and the United States.
Biographical Note
1894 August 30 Born, Bolota village, Russia (Poland)
1915 Graduated, seminary
1915 Student, Legal faculty, Rostov-on-Don University
1921 Priest, Kobrin, Poland
1934 Archpriest
1942 Archpriest, Orthodox church in Skidle village, Bielostok province, Poland
1945 Archpriest, various parishes of Displaced Persons' camps in Bavaria
1947 Archpriest, St. Nicholas Cathedral, Sao Paolo, Brazil
1960 Archpriest, Protection of the Holy Virgin Church, Los Angeles, California
1968 Archpriest, St. Myrrh Bearing Women Church, Bryte, California
? Died
Scope and Content
This collection consists mainly of Samoilovich's correspondence with members of the church hierarchy, fellow clergymen and parishioners, concerning his activities as an archpriest of various parishes from 1940 to 1968. It includes information on church matters in Germany during and after World War II, on church affairs in South America and California, as well as material on theologian Aleksandr Kalinnikovich Svitich.
The arrangement of the collection corresponds to the original order of the numerical files, with contents described in greater detail.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials and copyright to them (with some exceptions) are the property of the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
Series Description
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1940-1968., Boxes 1-3
  Consists mainly of correspondence with Russian Orthodox church officials, priests and parishioners. Includes some clippings, minutes of meetings, official documents and related matter, arranged numerically by original file number
- MISCELLANY, 1955-1966., Box 3
  Documents relating to the emigration of displaced persons to South America, printed matter (clippings, brochures) on religious subjects, sermons, and some correspondence
Container List
- Correspondence, 1940-1968
  - File 1. Metropolitan Serafim (Liade) (Archbishop of Berlin and Germany) (Box 1., Folder 1)
  - File 2. Archbishop Feodosii, of Brazil. Includes biographical information (printed matter) on Feodosii and the Brazilian Eparchiate (Folder 2-3)
  - File 3. Metropolitan Filaret (Folder 4)
  - File 4. Archbishop Tikhon, I. Sokolov, Z. A. Stankevich, Archbishop Serafim, A. Kotomkin, V. I. Arkhangels'skii, I. M. Andreev, Archbishop Aleksandr (Lovchii), Bishop Agapit, Archbishop Averkii, Metropolitan Anastasii, Metropolitan Aleksandr (Inozemtsev), Archbishop Feodor of Australia (Folder 5-6)
  - File 5. Archbishop Ioann (Maksimovich), Metropolitan Dionisii, Archbishop Grigorii, Archbishop Savva of Australia, Bishop Nektarii, Bishop Savva of Edmonton, Archbishop Leontii of Chile, Metropolitan Leontii of New York, Bishop Leontii of Geneva, Archbishop Vitalii of Canada, Archpriest N. Zhitinskii, A. V. Ignatiuk (Box 2., Folder 1)
  - File 6. N. N. Bylov, Fr. D. Gizetti, Archpresbyter G. Grabbe, A. Glinskii, Archpriest V. Glindskii (Folder 2)
  - File 7. Archpresbyter Pavel Kalinovich (Folder 3)
  - File 8. Igumen Kallist, Priest Leontii Kvartiruk, Archdeacon V. Kirik, N. V. Karpov, Rev. G. Kravchina, I. and E. Levitskii, Archpriest I. Ol'khovskii, Archpriest S. Starikov, A. Biriuk (Folder 4)
  - File 9. Bishop Nikandr, Rev. N. Paderin, Archpriest M. Pomazanskii, Archpriest M. Pol'skii, Archpriest I. Savich, Archpriest A. Svitich, O. K. Svir (Svirubskaia) (Folder 5)
  - File 10. Aleksandr Kalinnikovich Svitich. Includes clippings of Svitich's articles, obituaries (Box 3., Folder 1)
  - File 11. Archpriest M. Smirnov, S. Seletskii, Rev. P. Stupnitskii, K. F. Seredin, N. and E. Solodovnikov, A. Torlopova (Folder 2-3)
  - File 11a. "Bolgarskaia nedvizhimost'." Concerns the purchase of property for a church in Los Angeles (Folder 4)
  - File 12. Archpriest Gerasim Shorets (Folder 5)
- Miscellany, 1955-1966
  - "Germaniia i pereselencheskoe delo," 1942-1967. Consists mainly of correspondence, documents, and lists of names of Russians (displaced persons) wishing to emigrate to South America (Box 3., Folder 6)
  - Untitled file of printed matter (clippings, brochures, etc.) on religious subjects, sermons, and miscellaneous correspondence (Folder 7)